Today, I'm going to talk about the YouTube channel of Shokabo, a publisher specializing in natural science books
今日は、裳華房という自然科学書の出版社のYouTubeチャンネルの話をします
Huh? A publisher's channel? Is that what you're thinking?
え?出版社のチャンネル?って思いました?
But let me tell you, it's incredibly fascinating
でもこれがですね、めちゃくちゃ面白いんです
Shokabo's YouTube channel is truly wonderful
裳華房さんのYouTubeチャンネルが本当に素晴らしくて
If you're studying from science and engineering textbooks, this is a must-watch! I really want to recommend it
理工系の教科書を読んで勉強してる人なら必見!と推したいくらいなんです
And today, I want to introduce a mystery
そして今日は裳華房から出版されている
about an unfinished masterpiece published by Shokabo
未完の名著に関するミステリーを紹介したいと思います
Only the first volume was published
前編しか出版されていないのに
yet the first volume contains only the table of contents for the second volume
前編に後編の目次だけが載っている
This is a very mysterious textbook
とても不思議な教科書を巡る
filled with the passionate thoughts of researchers and editors
研究者と編集者の熱い思いが込められた
It's a truly moving story
とても感動的なエピソードなんです
So about today's video
で、今日の動画なんですが
Surprisingly, this is NOT a promotion for Shokabo
なんと、裳華房さんのプロモーションではありません。
Yes, so introducing someone else's channel doesn't earn me a single yen
はい、なので人様のチャンネルを紹介しても、私には一円の儲けにもならないんですよね。
But I wanted to express my gratitude for the work of publishers and editors who are essential for studying science and engineering
でも、理工系の学問の勉強に欠かせない出版社や編集者さんの仕事に感謝を少しでも伝えたい。
That's why I decided to make this video today
そんな気持ちで今日の動画を撮ることにしました。
So, won't you become a fan of Shokabo too?
というわけで、お前も裳華房のファンにならないか?
Now, for those who don't know what Shokabo is, let me give you a brief introduction
では、裳華房って何?という方もいらっしゃると思うので、簡単に紹介します。
Shokabo is a publisher of natural science books in physics, mathematics, and more
裳華房は物理や数学など、自然科学書の出版社です。
On their official website, their mascot character Umeko-chan introduces their bestselling books and YouTube channel
公式ウェブサイトを見ると、売れ筋の本やYouTubeチャンネルをマスコットキャラクターの梅子ちゃんが紹介してくれています。
Umeko-chan is really cute, isn't she?
梅子ちゃんとってもかわいいですよね
So what kind of videos does Shokabo's YouTube channel have?
で、この裳華房さんのYouTubeチャンネルにどんな動画があるかというと
First, there are lecture videos by the textbook authors themselves
まず教科書の著者自身の講義動画があります
Professor Junichiro Kishine from The Open University of Japan
放送大学の岸根順一郎先生が
has published a thermodynamics textbook through Shokabo
裳華房さんから熱力学の教科書を出版されているんですが
and amazingly, the professor himself appears
なんと先生ご自身が出演されて
to give thermodynamics lectures
熱力学の講義をしてくれているんです
You could say the publisher is also in the business of debuting researchers as YouTubers
出版社が研究者をYouTuberデビューさせる事業もやってる
That's one way to look at it
と見ることもできるかもしれませんね
And this is today's main topic
そしてこれが今日のメイントピックなんですが
There are videos where editors share behind-the-scenes stories
編集者が裏話を語ってくれる動画があるんです
These are really fascinating
これがですね、本当に面白くて
You might think that a YouTube channel from a physics and math publisher
物理や数学の本の出版社のYouTubeチャンネルなんて
would just be some boring corporate promotional channel, but
地味な企業の宣伝チャンネルなんじゃないの?って思う方もいるかもしれませんが
That's not the case at all!
全然違います!
Behind the publishing of natural science books lies a grand drama
自然科学書の出版の裏には壮大なドラマがあるんです
Watching this reminded me of "The Great Passage"
私はこれを見て「舟を編む」を思い出しました
I believe it's no exaggeration to say that Shokabo's YouTube is like a science version of "The Great Passage"
裳華房のYouTubeは理系版「舟を編む」だと言っても過言ではないと思っています
Let me briefly explain "The Great Passage"
「舟を編む」のことを簡単に説明すると
It's a novel by Shion Miura
これは三浦しをん先生の小説で
that won the Booksellers' Award in 2012
2012年に本屋大賞を受賞した作品です
The story is about publishing a Japanese dictionary
国語辞典の出版を題材にした物語で
and was a hit as a movie, anime, and drama
映画やアニメ、ドラマも大ヒットしました
Editors and linguists work together
編集者と国語学者が協力して
to create a Japanese dictionary
国語辞典を作っていくという
It's a superb intellectual entertainment
極上の知的エンターテイメントなんですね
I think one of the themes of "The Great Passage" is
私は「舟を編む」という作品のテーマの一つって
passing on one's work and way of life to future generations
自分の仕事、生き様を後世に伝えていくということだと思ってるんですよね
Publishing a Japanese dictionary is a massive project
国語辞典の出版って大プロジェクトで
In the story, 13 years pass
作中ではなんと13年の時間が経過します
That's how long such work takes
それくらい長い時間がかかる仕事なんです
Over 13 years, naturally the characters' life stages change
13年も経てば当然登場人物たちのライフステージも変わっていきますよね
Some get married, senior employees retire or pass away
結婚したり年配の社員は定年退職したりあるいは亡くなったり
And through all this, various forms of succession are depicted, I believe
そしてその中で様々な継承が描かれていると私は思ってます
And the exact same thing
でこれと全く同じことが
can be seen in Shokabo's YouTube channel
裳華房のYouTubeチャンネルでも見られるんです
Especially in the video I'm introducing today, you can feel this strongly
特に今日紹介する動画ではそれが強く感じられます
The main video I especially want to recommend
今日メインで特にオススメしたい
from Shokabo is this one
裳華房の動画がこちらです
The Unfinished Masterpiece
未完の名著
The Secret Left in the First Volume
前編に残された〇〇の秘密
And speaking about the passion for academic book editing
そして学術書編集への思いを語る
Connecting Knowledge
知をつなぐ
The title "Unfinished Masterpiece" is intriguing, isn't it?
未完の名著なんてタイトルからして気になりますよね
The video features
この動画で取り上げられているのが
Professor Isao Imai's "Fluid Mechanics (Volume 1)" textbook
今井功先生の流体力学(前編)という教科書です
This book was first published in 1973 and is still being reprinted as a masterpiece
この本1973年初版で今でも増刷されている名著なんです
There's also an e-book version, so you can have it without taking up shelf space
電子版もあるので本棚を圧迫せずに手元に置いておけるのも魅力ですね
But this book has a big mystery
でもこの本には大きな謎があるんです
The title says "Volume 1" but Volume 2 doesn't exist
それはタイトルに前編とあるのに後編が存在しないんです
Professor Imai passed away without ever writing Volume 2
今井功先生は後編を書かれることなく亡くなってしまったんですよね
But there's something even more mysterious
でももっと不思議なことがあります
This first volume contains the table of contents for the non-existent second volume
この前編には存在しない後編の目次が載っているんです
Look at this
見てくださいこれです
Volume 2 doesn't exist, yet there's a clear outline of what was planned
後編は存在しないのに何を書く予定だったのか
Only the table of contents remains
その目次だけがしっかり残っているんです
Boundary layers, turbulence, magnetohydrodynamics
境界層とか乱流とか電磁流体とか
Various topics are listed
いろんなトピックが並んでいます
I want to read about all of them...
どれも読んでみたい……
But there's no Volume 2
でも後編はないのに
Yet it's still being published as "Volume 1"
今でも前編と銘打って出版されているんです
Some readers say
読者の中には
if Volume 2 isn't coming out, the table of contents shouldn't be there
後編出ないなら目次はない方がいい
I've heard there are people with that opinion
という意見の方もいらっしゃるそうです
I can certainly understand that feeling
確かにそう思う気持ちもわかりますよね
There were really many voices of expectation from readers
読者からの期待の声も本当に多くて
Mr. Ono, an editor at Shokabo who appears in the video
動画に出演されている裳華房の編集者の小野さんという方が
said that when he was a young employee answering the company phone
若手社員だった頃に会社の電話番をしていると
he received so many calls asking "When will Volume 2 of Professor Imai's Fluid Mechanics come out?"
今井先生の流体力学の後編はいつ出るんですか?
There were really so many inquiries
という問い合わせが本当に多くて
He said there were times when he was afraid of the phone ringing
電話が鳴るのが怖かった時期もあったそうです
So why does this table of contents remain?
ではなぜこの目次は残り続けているのでしょうか
This mystery is revealed in the video
この謎が動画の中で明かされます
Editor Ono shares the story of his last meeting with Professor Imai
編集者の小野さんが今井先生と最後に会った時のエピソードを語ってくださっているんです
Mr. Ono visited Professor Imai's home many times
小野さんは今井先生のご自宅に何度も足を運んで
asking "How is the manuscript for Volume 2 coming along?"
「後編の原稿はいかがでしょうか？」と尋ねていたそうです
Professor Imai was already in his 80s at that time
今井先生は当時もう80代のご高齢で
and must have been struggling physically and health-wise
体力的、健康的に厳しかっただろうに
Yet Mr. Ono had to follow up on the manuscript as part of his job
それなのに仕事として原稿の催促をしなければならなかった
You can feel his difficulty in doing so
小野さんの心苦しさも伝わってきます
And the last time Mr. Ono met Professor Imai
そして小野さんが最後に今井先生とお会いした時
the professor said this
先生はこうおっしゃったそうです
"I'm truly sorry that I couldn't publish Volume 2"
「本当に後編出せなくて申し訳ないと思っています、
"However..." What did Professor Imai say after this?
ただ……」この後今井先生が何と語ったのか
Please watch the full video to find out
それはぜひ動画本編をご覧になってください
Professor Imai's conviction as a researcher
今井先生の研究者としての信念
Mr. Ono's sense of mission as an editor
小野さんの編集者としての使命感
You can feel them both
それが伝わってきます
I was deeply moved
私はめちゃくちゃ感動してしまいました
The table of contents for the non-existent Volume 2
この存在しない後編の目次は
is not just a table of contents
ただの目次じゃなくて
It represents Professor Imai's passion for fluid mechanics itself
今井先生の流体力学に対する想いそのものなんです
You could say it's homework that Professor Imai left for us
言うなれば今井先生が私たちに残してくれた宿題と考えることができるんですよね
That's why this table of contents remains to this day
だからこの目次は今も残り続けているんです
I was moved to see that this is the work of editors, the unsung heroes of knowledge transmission
これこそが知識の継承の裏方である編集者の仕事なんだと感動させられました
We can still read books published over 50 years ago thanks to the work of editors
私たちが50年以上前に出版された本を今でも読めるのは、編集者の方々の仕事のおかげなんです。
We tend to think that human knowledge has progressed continuously throughout history
私たちって、人類の知識は歴史が進むごとにどんどん進歩してきた、みたいに思いがちですけど、
But that's not true at all. Historically, much knowledge has been lost
実はそんなこと全然なくて、歴史的には失われた知識というのは数多くあります。
For example, the Library of Alexandria. This library was built in the 3rd century BC in what is now Alexandria, Egypt, and housed various books recording the knowledge of Greek civilization at the time. However, this library lost a vast amount of knowledge due to financial difficulties and wars.
例えば、アレクサンドリア図書館。現在のエジプトのアレクサンドリアにあった、当時のギリシャ文明の知識を記した様々な本が収蔵されていた、紀元前3世紀に建てられた図書館ですが、この図書館は財政難や戦乱などにより膨大な知識が失われてしまいました。
A more familiar example would be broken links to references in blog posts from 10 years ago. Even events from just 10 years ago are difficult to trace accurately now
身近な例だと10年前のブログのリンク先の参考文献とかもそうですね たった10年前の出来事でさえ当時のことを正確に追うことは難しいんです
Knowledge is easily lost without effort to maintain it. Publishers and editors do the tremendously important work of passing knowledge on to the next generation
知識って維持するための努力をしないと簡単に失われてしまうんですよね 出版社そして編集者は知識の次世代への継承というとてつもなく重要な仕事をしているんです
Shokabo's channel has many other truly valuable stories
裳華房のチャンネルには他にも本当に貴重なお話がたくさんあります
For example, Professor Ryogo Kubo's "Thermodynamics and Statistical Mechanics"
例えば久保亮五先生の「熱学・統計力学」
commonly known as "Kubo Statistics"
通称「久保統計」と呼ばれる教科書ですね
There's also a video introducing its behind-the-scenes story
その舞台裏を紹介する動画もあります
This was first published in 1961
これは1961年に出版
and a revised edition came out in 1998. It's a masterpiece among masterpieces
1998年に修訂版が出た名著中の名著ですけど
Mr. Ono was involved in editing the revised edition
小野さんは修訂版の編集に関わってらっしゃったそうです
"The Complete Solutions to Kubo Statistics" - anyone who has studied physics
「久保統計の完全解答」という物理を勉強したことがある人なら
would get excited
誰しもが胸を熱くする
or get chills at this topic. The episodes about it
あるいは背筋を凍らせる問いに対するエピソードが
are explained in a way that even those unfamiliar with Kubo Statistics can understand
久保統計を知らない人にも分かりやすく紹介されています
There are stories about mishaps when entertaining professors at the revised edition release
修訂版が出た時に先生方へ接待した時のやらかしエピソードや
and about how editor Ono sent a complaint postcard to Shokabo about a textbook when he was a student
編集者の小野さんが学生時代に裳華房の教科書にハガキでクレームを入れたら
only to end up reading his own complaint postcard after joining the company
入社後に自分で自分のクレームのハガキを読むハメになったみたいな
These human-interest episodes make it very relatable
人間味あふれるエピソードも含まれていて、とても親しみが持てるんですよね
It's really full of highlights
本当に見どころ満載です
So if you've become even a little interested in Shokabo's YouTube channel
というわけで裳華房のYouTubeチャンネル少しでも興味を持っていただけたなら
please check out the actual videos
ぜひ実際の動画を見てみてください
If you'd like
もしよかったら
please subscribe to Shokabo's YouTube channel and give them a like
裳華房YouTubeチャンネルのチャンネル登録と高評価
I'd really appreciate it
ぜひお願いします
Why am I asking you to subscribe and like
なんで私は自分のチャンネルじゃなくて
someone else's channel instead of my own?
人様のチャンネルのチャンネル登録と高評価をお願いしてるんでしょうね
Well, it doesn't earn me anything
いやー、何の儲けにもならないんですけどね
But it's truly wonderful content
でも本当に素晴らしいコンテンツなので
so I really hope you'll watch it
ぜひ見てほしいです
See you in the next video. Take care!
ではまた次回の動画までごきげんよう